Hi, my name is showman
...program manager with the visual...team in this session I'm going to talk about building
cplus-plus universal apps for windows stand using visual studio twenty fifteen.
So, this is roughly the jennifer today.
I'm going to provide a brief overview of some of the new concepts that windows
...introduces for app developers
we're going to dig deeper into this new concept called universal app platform.
Will take a look at how cplus-plus interacts with some of these new concepts that
the platform introduces and we'll talk about some of the cross platform features that...
introduces to help you build a apps for more than one platform?
And, then we'll take a look at demo of some of these new features in action.
So, it's not very surprising to see that
the convergence of the various windows platforms is a big team for windows
...we've been on this journey for a while all over the past few
...releases we have seen the operating system kernels for devices like xbox
...and phone getting...dot one we saw the programming model for
the windows apps and windows phone apps getting...and windows stand takes
this journey a step further and it now enables a single unify developer
experience that allows you to create a single app that can run on multiple devices.
Which is what we're calling the one windows platform you can now create a
single set of binary bundle them into a single app package upload them to a single
...store and still make them available to your end-users
on multiple devices on a wide variety of devices and even when
you're aberrant on these wide variety of devices windows...you to provide a
great...rich and very device appropriate experience irrespective of what
the what device the app is running on and you can do all of this using a single sdk
and a single set of tools from visual studio twenty fifteen?
So, one of the most important concepts that windows
...exposes to add developers existing called
...platform this is what really allows you to build a single app that can
...on multiple devicesbefore we understand universal...platform we
need to understand some of the building blocks that build it.
So, the first building-block is this notion of api contracts so
...and api contract is nothing but a bundle of operating system functionality
...api is instead of relying on
a specific api your app relies on api contract.
A platform is nothing but a bundle of api contracts so if you're app targets
of platform the app can rest assured that all the specified
api contracts would always be available all target devices that came to
support this platform and once we know what platform is you apr universal application platform
is nothing but the most column platform which consists of the most common
most popular and the most fundamental api contracts...are all always
...all devices and your app can always rely on them.
Understand also has ambitious goals in terms of being able to provide newer functionality
at a much faster cadence...to the end-users as well as the app
developers so this requires a solid versioning story and the way windows ten
handles this is by a creating and alignment between a version
of a platform and...versions of the underlying api contracts so you can understand this
alignment simply by opening of thisfile called platform that xml which
...inside the windows to
instigate if you look at this file it says that this platform just
call-you...with this specific version actually consists of
these three api contract with the specific versions now api contract
...change independently of each other what this means is that a future version of this
...platform might consist of.
The same versions of two of these api contract but a newer version of the
third api contract what this allows you as a developer is
...to target of well-defined concept called
up instead of having to worry about ever-changing operating
system versions and it also allows you to create a single app that you can right once and run
everywhere on multiple devices and also on multiple versions of the platform.
So, windows stand allows you to write adaptive code which does
the most device appropriate tang on every device and the wave understand
handle to this is by providing device specific extension is
...which are nothing but a bundle of
...device specific api contract so we have extension is
...case for mobile apps...for desktop apps
...mobile app you might want to make a phone call functionality which is specific to a
mobile app on for a desktop app you might want to connect usb printer which not
many mobile devices can do today so once you
have done that for from a developer perspective the...as simple
...referencing this platform extension sdk from inside your up app
projects and then visual studio automatically understand all the things that
...platform...and mix all the...time artifacts like headers
lives and metadata available to the...build time.
In addition to this of windows...also introduces this new concept of runtime api
...using which...app can.
Figure out what the devices capable
of at runtime before calling any api so this is a simple
...code example which shows you how you can use
...cpa called api information to figure out whether a type called hardware
buttons is present on the target device or not and if
...indeed present then you can go ahead and add
a new entangled to the camera pressed the event of the class.
So, what this allows you inability to create a single binary per architecture this
binary not only runs on various devices but on multiple versions of the platform?
If you have build...discuss apps the you must realize that visual superstores libraries
...important part of the...developer experience...envious
twenty thirteen we had we had two different runtime library packages
...to raps and windows phone apps
envious three-fifteen we have a single universal package that
the fulfills the runtime dependencies of all universal
...it contains a set of...that
run on all devices so not only this introduces a great improvements in
deployment but it also provides a great proof of concept about being able to create a
single set of binary on this platform which can run multiple devices.
The...time which has been a part of visual see this was libraries
for long is now actually a part of the windows to an operating system itself so,
this library will ship inside the operating system which means that you will
not see newer versions of the crt with successive releases of visual studio
you can still use new releases of visual studio and still rely on the fact that the
...time is always in the operating system in case of the see runtime library is used not only
...universal...but also
by classic desktop apps and some operating system components as wellagain,
this introduces the now.
Much simplicity of deployment it provides disk space usage gains
and the sense that there are fewer
...arterials floating around and it also provides a performance
...benefits because you have fewer runtime dealers loaded...you process at any time.
This is of course a first step towards our eventual goal of arriving
at this stage when we have a set of binary stable visual
...libraries which can be freely used by even future versions of the compiler
tools it.
Not being able to create a single binary is great but these days
...user apps on multiple devices and
the not only expect the apps to work but...expect the apps to work great
they expect the apps to provide the richest most device appropriate experience based on
whatever the target device form factor is so if you
...app while running on a pc or a tablet
is just a magnified version of how it looks like on phone then you're probably missing a trick.
Now in this theory also of windows
...provides grid differences such as a custom visual
state triggers which allow your and py to?
Adapt based on changes such as screen orientation and size
...so this is a simple example
of some example code that changes the orientation of a panel from
...vertical to horizontal if the if the minimum window
...exceeds a particular threshold.
In addition to this windows ten
also provides some building controls which are automatically adaptive and they do the
right thing depending on the target operating environment.
So, visualize that windows is not the only platform you build your apps for there
are other popular platforms as well and we also realize that cplus-plus by
design is across platform language so we want to help you build your see
...apps cross platform irrespective of whatever platform your targeting and you've done a
bunch of things in that area as well the first and the most important thing is
adding a number of language and libraries conformance features to
our compilers in libraries we've done a lot of work to implement major pieces of
...eleven and...fourteen standards
this allows you as an app developer to write cross platform code that can build not
all using visual cplus-plus but using other standard compliant compilers as
well for other platforms and this also expanse the list of open-source
...justice libraries which are very popular on other platforms like
...android and can now be easily used for windows apps as well as...you twenty fifteen?
Obvious now provides native support for building
...android apps...done this by integrating open-source tools...like
...into visual studio itself and keeping with the spirit of being
...platform we've done a lot of work to allow
you to manager across platforms you just as code base which can be shared in
multiple mobile platform maps there's a separate session that goes into much more detail on the specific
...if you're interested in that.
And, that bring this to the demo so let us jump into the demo and look, at the product in action.
One thing you need to know about building windows ten apps is that developer tooling
for these apps...optional install feature in visual studio you have to
remember to select that as an option while installing bs once you select that option
you could the right tools for all languages like cplus-plus
csharp and javascript anyway here I have visual
student twenty fifteen running on a windows ten machine I've already installed all
the quite tools so let's go ahead and create a universal...
If you go to...new project under visual semesters windows,
windows universal you'll see a bunch of project templates like xhtml direct
...dl static library windows runtime so on for
now I'll just select of dank zum lab and...okay.
Now...project has been created inside the id let's take a look at some windows
...specific things in your project structure.
If you look at the solution explorer under the references node.
You will notice these api contracts these content...part of the universal
app platform so there always added to all universal project created by vs
...these contracts which are just windows metadata
files are passed along to the...compiler which understands these contract
...and therefore allows you to call any api define them.
You also notice that all this is a universal project doesn't have
anything called shared code and that's because if...app is relying only on the api
contracts contain inside the uyvy...all the code inside your app is
...code and it can always...all devices without requiring to build
...for this job and phone and if you want to see evidence that.
You could open of this file called a package or epics
...this file basically determines the target of your
of your application package and in the dependency section.
And, you can see that your app targets a device family called windows
...which means that you can on xbox desktop.
Okay, it's close these files now and moving on the...some simpleexample code.
I would open the main page the...file...emulator and overwrite some
...code and we'll see how the code looks like on...the local machine and inside
...mobile emulator.
So,...is really simple...block and
...some nice text like hello windows can.
And, I...position in the center of the window and.
And, the guid a nice fond and close it out.
So, let's have five.
Just build and run this up on the local machines was to.
So, you see the app loaded...nothing too surprising here as expected the text
appears in the center of the window the only new thing is that this is not a full-screen
app which...which is a new thing for windows dan universe...running on desktop.
So, let's...for now.
And, now instead of runningthe app
...the local machine...launched the...on a mobile emulator.
So, one thing you notice here is
that visual studio did not need to build the app again it is just using the same set of
binary and deploying them on to the mobile emulator this is how the app looks like on
emulator as you can see the textile...in the center and this is in fact...full-screen
up which is what makes sense for a mobile device without keyboard and mouse so this is great
what if I app is a scenario where he wants to do something specific while running on
a phone device let's go and closes up and look at that scenario.
And, that case the first thing you want to do is added reference.
To this thing called the microsoft mobile extension instigate.
As you can notice by doing this visual studio pulls in all the phone specific api
contracts contained inside this...and they're made available to the compiler and
...so now we can go ahead and make
...specifically...calls but I still want to make sure that my at continues to do the right
thing for desktop to enable that scenario I can use the windows ten at
runtime you vegetation using which and app can figure out the capability of a
device that runtime so let's open of the main page...rgb file.
And, the constructor of the main page...some code.
I'm calling the new api information api provided by windows...
To figure out.
Is present...art and the divx I'm looking for?
Is...core hardware buttons and depending on with the
...of resin and art my app can determine whether this is a mobile device...
And, if the hardware buttons are indeed present.
I'll go ahead...
To the camera pressed event and adding anyone...using the id is
actually really simple you just need to hit that twice.
And, it actually goes ahead and creative dummy implementation for you don't
want system implementation so I'll delete discord and just simply bubba message
dialogue every time the...is clicked...
Created...and I'll just go ahead and.
Show the dialogue.
...this up now...a five.
So, it's still the same map or when I click on the camera button inside the mobile
...which you'll see the message...pops up?
And, run it again on the local machine.
You'll see that there's no change in the app continues to run as it used to earlier.
So, let's go...vision...you here.
So, that was a simple example of universal
...app...not take a look at a slightly more complex example.
Here I have the solution with...projects one is a...resemble project called face finder.
And, the second is a superstars windows runtime component called ninety
...detect as you can get from the name this
app will have something to do with detecting faces in pictures.
References we...in...component.
References something called an open cv...so this is basically the...platform
superstars image processing live recorded open cv built using visual cplus-plus
twenty fifteen and neatly packaged into and extension sdk which can be
easily used in any universal project in this case...component simply
uses open cv api to perform face detection on a set of pictures.
Let's look at the way of the app.
As you can see the way of the app is a very simple example with the stack panel that has to
reduce.
Both of which display some images using...data...to display the pictures and
...display the detected faces they just go ahead and run the app.
On the local machine and see what it looks like.
Here's app is hit the first buttoned load the images
which brings of this dialog and I can select all the images in this dialog and
And, all the images are displayed in a nice green
...in my window and I can hit the second retinal
detect faces and as you can see the faces are being detected...inside the green view.
If I resize this...window you'll notice that there's already some amount of adaptive
...in the way...automatically really
out when the windows size changes however after a certain point.
It falls apart and edwin
...narrow window size can highly see the bottom review.
We look into this problem later.
For knowledge is...
And, instead of launching it on the local machine dislodged...the mobile emulator.
So, we have the same...actually launching...inside the emulator and when I try to load the images?
I don't see anything here because all the pictures
that represent on my desktop are not really present on the mobile emulator this means that in case of
a phone the app...have to figure out a different way of
...the images this is a second problem will need to look into.
They just go back to the main page, for example, and, see what happens when you click the load button.
We have this event...load button click I can easily go to definition of
thisfunction just by selecting good definition.
And, this brings me do this...handler?
Car load button underscore click.
And, you can see that uses the file open beaker api to a load
set of images and then it has some internal logic to
display those images in the...incitement...
However, we know that there are no images...the...so instead of loading the images from
there we load them from within the app itself now I've already added.
All the images to this folder called people in...project all
any to do now is to loaded from within my app at runtime.
In order to do that I'll go ahead and uncommon discord.
When this could does?
Checks for the presence of a type called hardware burton's...based on which due to
...that the app is actually running on a mobile device and in that
...to the install location of the app looks for...called people and load
all the images from that folder now it doesn't actually do anything after that.
What needs to happen here is just to display the images that
...already exist in the video portion here?
And, instead of duplicating it I will go ahead and use the new
id factoring feature called extract method to create a separate...out of it.
I'll give it a name called in display.
Selected files.
And, once this implementation has been created I'll copy
disappear called and based and discord that I've just...as well.
But, I still want to make sure that...app continues to do the right thing when it is running on non mobile
devices like desktop in order to do that I will put this bottom block.
Into...section.
Okay, so,...one problem solved there...not look at the problem of the incorrect
...layout so I'll go back to the main visual examine.
You can see that here's a stack panel which contains to reviews which are ...stacked.
So, I need to do now is ...comment this simple example...
To seminal core creates a custom visual
state trigger that dynamically changes the orientation and a few
...properties based on the width of the window so thi this file.
And, just turned five.
So, the app loads.
...button.
I can see the images getting...from within the average-size and...detect button.
I see...are also getting...in...next to the initial review.
Let's close out now.
And, again, run it on local machine.
Even in case of a local machine you'll notice that the app actually did not have to be
rebuild the same binary is actually...to local machine now and continue to
And, again, select all the images from here and open.
...detect faces.
...my app is still fluid.
But, after a certain threshold my custom visual trigger logic takes over
and displays the to reviews side-by-side rather than on top of each other.
So, that was a brief overview of building...universal apps using
...two-twenty fifteen if you're interested in learning more here are some resources the receive just
as blog provides information about all the work that...just
assume does and we have blog for windows developer experiences well we hope you
like these features and we looking forward to feedback thanks for watching.